<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Coppies of letters sent from personages of accompt vnto divers personages of worth in London truely relating all such remarkable occurrences as haue hapned in the Palatinate from the 30th of May to the 11 of Iune. Amongst which, the prise that Count Mansfield hath taken from the Bavarian. As also the mis-hap of the Duke of Brunswicke in his passage over the river of Mayne. Likewise a relation of divers strange and miraculous accidents, falling out thereabouts. By Doctor Welles and others. Printed this 22. of Iune 1622.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.56A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107085</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842788</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842788</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08159)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 682:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Coppies of letters sent from personages of accompt vnto divers personages of worth in London truely relating all such remarkable occurrences as haue hapned in the Palatinate from the 30th of May to the 11 of Iune. Amongst which, the prise that Count Mansfield hath taken from the Bavarian. As also the mis-hap of the Duke of Brunswicke in his passage over the river of Mayne. Likewise a relation of divers strange and miraculous accidents, falling out thereabouts. By Doctor Welles and others. Printed this 22. of Iune 1622.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Iohn Bartlet, and are to be sold at  his shop in Cheap-side, at the gilt Cup in the Gold smiths row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The copy catalogued is a variant; other copies have date 21. of Iune.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 19128.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19128 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Palatinate (Germany) --  History --  Frederick V, 1610-1623.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7476:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 87 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:7476:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 87 -->
            <p>COPPIES OF LETTERS SENT FROM PERSONAGES Of Accompt vnto divers Perſonages of Worth in <hi>London;</hi> Truely relating all ſuch remarkable Occurrences as haue hapned in the <hi>Palatinate</hi> from the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> to the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of IVNE.</p>
            <p>Amongſt which, the Priſe that Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> hath taken from the <hi>Bavarian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo the Miſ-hap of the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> in his paſſage over the River of <hi>MAYNE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe a Relation of divers ſtrange and miraculous Accidents, falling out thereabouts.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Doctor Welles</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>Printed this 22. of <hi>Iune</hi> 1622.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bartlet,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> at the gilt Cup in the Gold-ſmiths Row. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7476:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 88 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:7476:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 88 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>To the courteous Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Theſe are to advertiſe thee that theſe Letters are Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without the privitie of thoſe that ſent them, but I ſuppoſe that they will not take it offencively, that all ſuch as are well-willers to the cauſe of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> ſhould bee made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the common occurrences which fall out there, and I ſuppoſe they would the rather ſuffer it, if they knew or were made acquainted with the falſe Rumors which often paſſe heere for current, vntill wee heare the contrary by ſuch Letters as theſe are: I haue not prefixed any long preamble to the enſuing Relation, neither is it ſtuffed with any ſuperfluous coniectures, but you haue them printed in the ſame wordes and phraſe in which I received them.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:7476:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 89 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7476:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 89 -->
            <head>COPIES OF LETTERS Sent from perſonages of accompt vnto divers perſonages of Worth in <hi>London,</hi> truely relating all ſuch <hi>remarkeable Occurrences as haue</hi> hapned in the <hi>Palatinate</hi> from the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> to the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of IVNE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom <hi>Hannaw</hi> within theſe two dayes are come together all the Forces the Emperor, <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops can make with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſix Germaine myles of vs. The King hath his Forces together, the one halfe in <hi>Ments</hi> Lands, the King in <hi>Darmſtradts</hi> Lands. <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> is not yet with the King, he is this day about a myle from <hi>Freeſburg</hi> in the Watterewe, foure myles from vs. The King hath or ſhall haue from <hi>Franckford</hi> an 100000. Reeks Dollars. The <hi>Bavarian</hi> ſouldiers fall daily to <hi>Mansfield,</hi> I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7476:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 90 -->
haire ſeene it, and haue heard it of his offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, that they goe twelue or ſixteene in a day out of a Company. And two dayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe there was money going to pay for foure Moneths, but <hi>Mansfeilds</hi> Souldiers tooke it.</p>
            <p>There were three Hathorn Trees by <hi>Darmſtadt,</hi> which were ſpotted all over on the leaues as with blood; they are in <hi>Franckford</hi> to be ſeene; when they are wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed they will go off, but come on againe. For three weeks word came from <hi>Valtaline,</hi> from the Griſons, that the folke had ſlaine all <hi>Leopoldus</hi> Forces he had left there, for he had alſo put the <hi>Valtalines</hi> to the ſword for them of their Religion, and that after ſuch crueltie, as the like hath not bin heard of. This weeke Newes came, that in a towne called <hi>Bunfen,</hi> there were but fiftie men left in habitants; and many women, who putting themſelues into mens apparell, ſlew at ſeverall times two thouſand of the Papiſts their enemies: it is accounted here a worke and a wonder of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>MAINHEM <date>2. of IVNE.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:7476:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 90 -->
            <opener>
               <dateline>Mainhem <date>the 2. of Iune, 1622. <hi>Old Stile.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>MY L. <hi>Chicheſter</hi> arived here on Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day laſt, to my Lord Generals great comfort, and the whole troupes. Barron <hi>Tilley</hi> ſtrengthened with his freſh ſupplies, which were 5000. foote and 1000. horſe, marched towardes the Maine, to hinder Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> and Marquis <hi>Baden,</hi> from meeting with the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick.</hi> Now the paſſage aimed at on both ſides was <hi>Aſhenburge</hi> a Towne of the Biſhop of <hi>Ments</hi> vpon the Maine, where there is a Bridge. The Count <hi>Mansfeilds</hi> Army came about <hi>Darmſtat,</hi> one Thurſday was ſevennight, and there ſtaid the comming of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis which was Sunday: to conclude it was Teuſday before they marched from their quarters, in the <hi>Lantgraues</hi> Countrey towards this <hi>Aſhenburge,</hi> when beeing by <hi>Dippergen</hi> a ſmall Towne, which ranſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it ſelfe at 15000. <hi>Lor.</hi> advertiſement came of the Barron <hi>Tillies</hi> hauing poſſeſſed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7476:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 91 -->
himſelfe of the paſſage, and that hee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched directly towards them with a great power, weied to bee (by the coniecture) of the Barron <hi>Anhalts</hi> forces and moſt of <hi>Gonſales</hi> with him 30000. and the horſe ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly armed from top to toe as they ſay. Our Armie then thought of a faire retrait, and applied to it by the ſame way they advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and lay the ſame night in Armes: on Wedneſday they retreated towards <hi>Openhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi> bridg and lodged about <hi>Girah.</hi> On thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day (which was a very great march) they came on this ſide <hi>Benſheim,</hi> The Enemie all this while following without any thing done, on Fryday morning our two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hauing ſo diſpoſed of themſelues, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by ſeverall paſſages to <hi>Loreſh,</hi> leaſt the enemie ſhould cut betweene them and <hi>Mainhem,</hi> but were no ſooner riſen, but the Enemie appeared, and with a body of Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſiers, charged the rereward of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Baden,</hi> wher his Lieutenant General Colonell <hi>Golſtein</hi> a man much lamented for his courage and vnderſtanding was at the firſt ſhot ſlaine. But ſince that written newes came from the Enemies Leaguer
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7476:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 91 -->
that hee is liuing ſhot in the head, but not mortally, and his horſe put to the worſe, but the preſſe of the enemy was kept vp by the Rereward of Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> horſe, the Regiment of Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Megant,</hi> and were forced to a diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly retreat. Note the enemies foote ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer came vp, which if they had, the whole muſt needes haue beene engaged. Thus skirmiſhing continued in the rere ſomewhat ſharpely by fits, till towardes night: the danger on euery ſide was by the Chiefes vigilance preuented, and the eſtimate of men ſlaine on both ſides is betweene 3. or 4. hundred, but till a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular view bee taken of the particular companies by each Captaine, the iuſt number of thoſe that are wanting can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be knowne. In this skirmiſh his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty ſhewed himſelfe (as before) moſt forward and valorous to the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of others.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Landgraue</hi> of <hi>Darmſtart</hi> and his yonger ſonne are inuited hither, and lodged with the King at the Citadell, the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> came ſuddenly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exſpectedly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7476:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 92 -->
vpon the <hi>Landgraue</hi> of <hi>Darm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat,</hi> ſo that hee came to meete the King withall ſpeeding demonſtrations of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and much complement, which hee would haue ſpared if the king had not brought a force with him able to fleece the <hi>Landgraue,</hi> the King notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding did not truſt him; but ſhewed him an intercepted letter of his, whereat he was ſilent, and moſt of the Cattle in his countrey are driuen into the <hi>Pallati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> to make ſupply of fleſh there.</p>
            <p>The Arch Duke <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poldus</hi> at my ſince his retreat from <hi>Hagenaw</hi> hath bene in a grea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſumption, what with muting and a great different betweene the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> ſouldiers, a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo by the <hi>Switzers</hi> who are ſayde to haue killed a great number of them.</p>
            <p>The Count <hi>Leuenſteine</hi> in a letter to my Lord, takes notice of a Caſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iere</hi> and <hi>Zurich,</hi> taken from the <hi>Spaniard</hi> with three peeces of Canon which the Citizens haue now before <hi>Mainfelt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We here nothing from aboue, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7476:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 92 -->
great preparations (if the armies on foot ſuffiſe not) againſt the poore <hi>Palatinate.</hi> Whether our army will aduenture once more ouer the Neckar, or take ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe, leaue.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Germaine</hi> Prince of the houſe of the <hi>Rhinegraues,</hi> and a Count of the houſe of the <hi>Mansfields</hi> were taken, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers meaner of Officers, on the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſide was a Collonell ſlaine in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate armour, by a bullet in his face when hee lifted vp his helmet to take cold aire. And many other Officers of horſe, we count it a great bleſſing of God that in a retreat of thirty miles, we loſt no baggage, nor more men the enemy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline>From <hi>Mainheim,</hi> 
                  <date>Iune 6. 1622.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>You will happily in few dayes heare of a ſcoffe ſooner then of armes, or a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer of hoſtility, which makes as much, wee haue the Marqueſſe of <hi>Baden</hi> and Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> here with vs, with both their armies, which are ſhortly elſe where to be beſtowed or diſcharged of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7476:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 93 -->
attending the good ſucceſſe of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The <hi>Bauarians</hi> forces are in <hi>Darmſtrats</hi> countrey in a readineſſe to oppoſe what may be attempted by the duke of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> in his paſſage vpward: but it is conceited that the endeauours of the Lord Ambaſſador here, and thoſe at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> will put a barre betweene them, here is a ſpeech that the <hi>Turke</hi> is pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring downe his forces vpon Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but hauing no ground for it other then a common report, you ſhall take it accordingly. This day the king ſent 2. Gentlemen to <hi>Bruſſels</hi> as doth alſo the Marqueſſe of <hi>Baden,</hi> there to treate for them: my Lord Ambaſſador ſent his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to <hi>Gonſalo Tilly,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> who is neere to <hi>Aſhenburg.</hi> Moſt of the Marqueſſe his forces are put into Garriſon at <hi>Hidelberg, Frankendale,</hi> and <hi>Mainheim:</hi> my Lord Ambaſſador hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued them for 3. weekes into the king our ſoueraigns pay; he payes ſo many as makes the number vp, with theſe my Lord Generall already hath, in that ſpace of three weekes it is thought that they of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7476:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 93 -->
               <hi>Bruſſels</hi> will either conclude or breake off.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> hath taken <hi>Haſteon;</hi> the riuer of <hi>Main,</hi> and made a bridge ouer it, he hath ſixe Regiments of foote, and eighty Cornet of horſe.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> horſe went to meete the Duke of <hi>Brunſwickes</hi> forces, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his foote.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline>From <hi>Mainheim</hi> 
                  <date>the 11. of <hi>Iune.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>In haſt I deſire to preſent my loue, &amp; tell you that Barron <hi>Tilly</hi> and <hi>Gonſalo</hi> are gone with all the forces they can make ouer the <hi>Main</hi> to ſee if they can finde out the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> who lay intren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at a place called <hi>Hoeſt</hi> within a Dutch league of <hi>Frankford,</hi> where the Duke lay ready to encounter him, there is great diſaduantage in their forces, but we hope that it will bee made vp by the aduantage of the ground, it is apparant by the great preparation of the campe that he hopeth to ſwallow vp the Duke, but wee hope it ſhall turne to the aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7476:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 94 -->
of the Dukes honor, the duke hath had many skirmiſhes with them, wherein he hath had the better of them We haue, and you will heare of a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table defeate of the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> by <hi>Francford</hi> to the loſſe and ſcattering of the whole army, but God be thanked it is not true but what is the truth is hard to ſay, the likelieſt is, that in paſſing the <hi>Main</hi> towards a bridge by <hi>Hoeſt</hi> below <hi>Franckford, Tilly</hi> who is now ſayd to bee 30000. at leaſt, with three ſupplyes from aboue, from <hi>Bohemia, Bauaria,</hi> and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and the Duke had but two ſmall peeces: and the Barron of <hi>Anhoults</hi> occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath broke the bridge with thirteen peeces of Canon, where the foote were moſt paſſed, and put the horſe to ſwim, and ſo tooke much of the baggage and ſome men therewith, but God be praiſed the body of the Army ioynes this night with the kings, we hope.</p>
            <p>The Army hath laine euer ſine they came out of <hi>Darmſtat</hi> here by <hi>Mainheim.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7476:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 94 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
